In this sequence, we will look at how we can
get information in and out of an OCaml program.
But let me just first remind you something.
Up to now, we have been using the OCaml toplevel
extensively, it is very handy.
It reads our program incrementaly phrase by
phrase
and it prints the result of the execution
of our programs.
That is fantastic because up to now
we could really do all this work without discovering
a single input/output operation:
everything was done by the toplevel for us.
But in real programs, of course you need to
be able to read and write to a file,
to a standard input, a standard output.
OCaml offers a rich set of I/O primitives.
Now we will look at some of them here,
but first of all, we need to meet a strange
type which is called the unit type,
which is very useful when you start doing
operation that have side effects like
input/output operations.
So let's meet the unit type.
Look at this strange expression, open parenthesis
and close parenthesis, and nothing else.
If we hit 'return', the system tells us that
we have defined some value which is again
(), of a type we didn't know,
which is called unit.
Well, this unit type is a typical type you
find as input or as a result type with functions
with side-effets.
It has only one value, which we also call
unit, and which is just written ().
That is a special syntax for the only value
of this unit type.
This may look like a strange syntax for a
unique value of a type, but it has precise
reasons to be there,
this will be clear just in a few slides.
Now that we have met this unit type, this
(), it doesn't shock us too much anymore,
let's look at the functions for input and
output.
The first one we can use is for performing
simple output: printing an integer.
There is a function predefined for you which
is called print_int,
the type is actually int -> unit, so what
does it do?
It takes an interger in input, prints the
integer on the standard output
and returns the single value () of the unit
type.
So, for example let's print the integer 12345.
We hit 'return', this is the result.
To understand what is going on here in the
standard output
is important to understand that the first
thing that has happened
is that the printing function has really printed
on the standard output
the number 12345 and just stopped there.
Just after that, the toplevel starts printing
its own message,
which says basically that the evaluation is returning
the value () of the unit type,
and there is no identifier bound to it, I
mean the '- :'
We can also perform simple input operations,
there is a predefined function which is called
read_line for you.
This is a type that says: takes a unit and
gives you back a string.
What actually really happens is that this
function waits for a input value of type unit,
there is juste one, I mean this (),
and as soon as it gets this value it read
a line of characters from the standard input
as a string,
and returns it to us.
So for example let's try to read a line, now
you write read_line,
you need to give a parameter of unit type,
the only one we know is just ().
When we hit 'return', the system waits for
our input, so I write "some text" here,
and as soon as I hit 'Enter', the result which
I get from the system
is the string containing "some text", of type
string.
I mean ,what happens really:
read_line receives the argument (),
starts reading from the standard input,
after we type "some text" and hit 'return',
the toplevel prints its message which says:
the evaluation returns a value, a string,
of the string type,
and there is no identifer bound to it.
Very simple two situations: printing an integer
or reading a line.
Now I think we are ready to understand the
particular choice of the syntax here,
so it should be easy to see now why for the
unique value of the unit type,
it has been chosen to use ().
Because read_line for example, the example
I've shown before,
written this way really looks like a function
with no arguments in other languages,
which you use for, for example, performing
side effects.
That's very familiar for outsiders,
but for us now that we are learning this OCaml
programming language,
we should remember that is really means the
read_line function applied to one argument,
which happens to be of the unit type, so it
happens to be written ().
Well, of course when we are starting to do
input and output,
there are many other base types that can be
printed,
so you have a function for printing characters,
strings, floating points.
You have a functions for printing a newline,
flushing the standard output,
and there is much much more available,
so you can manipulate standard input, standard output and standard error,
create, open and close files,
read and write on channels,
perform sophisticated operations like scanf...
This is beautiful in this language, scanf,
unlike what happens in C, is really well-typed.
I do recommand that you look at the manual
section of Pervasives
to get an idea on this kind of functions.
But a word of warning,
some of these functions make no sense when
you are running them inside a browser,
like the exercise and environment we are providing
to you,
and so they are not implemented in the toplevel
running in your browser.
You should just stick to printing and reading
lines.
To sum up, we have discovered the unit type,
the input and output functions.
So unit type as soon as you see it, in general,
you suspect there is some side effect going
on,
it is often used with functions with side-effects.
When you see something like read_line (), coming
from another programming language,
you could think this is a function with
0 parameters.
It is really a function with one parameter that
happens to be of the unit type.
And now, we know how to perform basic input/output
operations,
but if you want to know more, do not hesitate
in looking at the reference manual for more
information.