In this sequence, we will discover
what are called references in OCaml
which are similar to variables
in other programming languages.
What are variables in typical
imperative languages?
Let's consider this little fragment
of program
that could be part of a C or Java program.
The first line is a definition of a variable
i.
i is a name of the variable,
it is initialised to 0.
This name i may refer to a memory cell
when it is put on the left of the = sign
(it's the memory cell that you are writing)
or to the contents of a memory cell
typically when it is on the right of the = sign.
But this can become pretty complicated,
in general you can make knots in your head
thinking about l-values, r-values
in different programming languages.
Well if you really want to have variables
in OCaml
we can use the mutable records
we have just discovered
to get the same effect.
So, again, let's consider this program:
an integer variable i initialized to 0
and then later on somebody decided
to increment this value by adding 1 to it.
But this can be written in OCaml
by defining a record type
we will call it "reference cell", refcell,
that has just one field, which is called content,
of type integer
and we define this field as mutable.
Now the first line of the imperative program
we have there
int i = 0 can be actually written as
let i be a name of record refcell
which is initialized with the content field
equal to 0.
And then the modification can be
done in place
in the second line you see here.
We're saying we are updating
the content field of i
with the old value of this content field
plus one.
Here, this update operator clearly indicates
what is read and what is written.
In OCaml actually, you have
a predefined ref type
that is defined exactly this way,
but has its special syntax
to be used in a more concise way.
Actually, this is called a reference type.
As well, its instances, we all call them
references.
The definition is exactly like this:
we define a polymorphic record type
with a mutable, single field named contents
that contains the information
we want to store.
This comes with a really convenient
syntactic support:
you have a function, predefined for you,
it is also called ref,
that is able to create a reference:
we pass the function the value to store
in the reference, and it provides us
with a reference initialized to this
particular value.
Now you have a prefix operator !, here,
which is used to explicitely indicate
you want to read the content of the reference.
And then you have an infix operator,
:= which is used to perform update of
the content of the reference.
So this will mean
"update the content of the reference r
by putting in there the value v".
Let us see this at work on a simple example.
Well, so, now let's get familiar with the references.
We start with a very simple example:
here, on the first line, we are defining
an identifier i, which is a name for a reference
that contains zero.
So you remember, this ref function here
takes a value and creates a cell
that contains exactly that value.
So we pass it to the interpreter,
and you see
now what the compiler tells us:
that he has seen the definition of the identifier
i
that is a name of a reference cell
containing an integer
and the contents is really this zero here,
inside.
Well, again, if now I try to look at what
is i,
I get the same result, it is always this reference
cell
with content zero.
Now let's start to modify the reference.
We have seen that to modify a reference
to make an update,
we have this := operator
that changes the content of the reference
cell on the left,
by the value which is
on the right of the colon-equal sign.
And what is the value we are taking here?
We are adding 1 to the content of the i
reference.
And the content is taken by this bang operator
here.
So we would expect to see, now,
i changing value moving to 1.
Well the system tells us that this
operation has been performed.
As it is only working by side-effect,
the result is of unit type.
Now if we look at i again, now the content
of the reference cell has been changed
and contains 1, as expected.
So basically, this is a way of simulating
variables,
but the difference is now, for us
it is really clear when we are taking the
content of the variable,
you see, we're taking this content operator
with !
and when we are updating the content of the
variable,
by this update operator :=.
Ok, so let's see an example:
imagine we want to compute
the integer base to logarithm of the integer
n
well, a very easy way of doing this is just
counting
how many time you can divide
this integer by two, before getting below
one.
So let's program it the same way you would
do it
in other programming languages.
In imperative programming languages
we define the log2int function: it takes
an integer n as a parameter
then we define two "variables" -- now we know
the real name here is "references":
one named count, which is a reference
initialized to 0,
and another named v, which is initialized
to the value n
which has been passed as a parameter.
Now what we do:
we do a simple while loop
that keeps dividing the original integer by
until it goes below, or equal, to 1,
and at the same time, increments this counter
to keep track of how many times
we did this operation.
At the end of the loop, we return the content
of this counter count.
So we can pass the definition to the compiler.
You see the compiler tells you it is just
a function
that takes an integer and return an integer
and as you can expect, the base 2 logarithm of
16 is really 4,
of 1024 is 10
and of one million, it is 19.
Ok, so let's try now something
a little more sophisticated:
let's try to read a list of integers
from the standard input.
Well, we can start by defining a function
that reads an integer.
It's pretty easy, we just use the read_line
function
we already know.
This will return a string, and then we convert
it to an integer.
By the way, this is a function which is predefined
in OCaml.
It is defined exactly this way.
Then, to write a read_intlist function,
what we can do,
doing it the really imperative way:
we use a "variable", our reference,
which is initialized to the empty list
and this variable will be updated in a loop
here
which is defined in a new function we will
call doread.
This is an infinite loop: while true do ... done,
it will never stop, and
in this loop, we read an integer,
we add it in front of the content of our l
variable
and update the content of our l variable.
So you see here again we are taking the content
of the value of l,
do the concatenation
with the integer we have just read, and then
use this value to update the content of l,
so we have a new value coming out.
Well, when will this loop stop?
As soon as we get an exceptional condition,
this can happen if you type something which
is not an integer, so read_int will raise
an exception or,
for example, if you finish the standard
input.
As soon as we get an exception, we want
to catch it
so this is why we have a try ... with around
this infinite loop
and when the exception raises, the computation
is stopped and we just return ().
Now that we have these two elements,
I mean our reference and the infinite loop,
we can just write do_read (),
this will read until we stop the computation
with an exception
and as soon as we have done this,
we will find inside our variable l
all the integers we have typed in
but they are in reverse order,
so to put them
in the right order
we just the call the List.rev function
on top of this.
So let's see if this really works
as expected.
Fine, so our compiler is happy,
the type checked properly
and we have defined a function
that waits for a unit element
and returns the integers list read
on the standard input.
So, let's try it out.
Ok, you see, now, this read_int has been
called
for the first time,
we have a popup in our environment
which is used to read the line.
I will enter the integer one.
Then it keeps coming up again, so,
let's type 2, 3, 4, 5...
Now I want to stop this so I'll enter something
which is not an integer.
And here it is, we get our integer list,
in the proper order.
So to sum up, the usual variables in
imperative languages can be implemented
via mutable records.
This is exactly what
can be done in OCaml.
The notion of memory cell,
and of contents of memory cell
in this interpretation with mutable records,
are clearly distinguished
and we have a special syntax which is available
for writing more concise programs
using references.
So after having seen all these notions in this
week,
we have concluded our short exploration
on the imperative features
of the OCaml language.
So if you really want, you can write
fully imperative programs in the language.
But our recommendation is to use these
features only where they are really, really
needed
for efficiency reasons.