Well, in this sequence, we will learn how
to use exceptions in the OCaml programming
language.
Well, what are exceptions?
OCaml provides exceptions, which are useful
for
signaling and handling exceptional conditions,
like in many other programming languages,
but here, exceptions are just constructors
of a special sum type written exn but we
all call it exception anyway.
This constructor
can have arguments like all other constructors.
So it seems like just typical constructor
of sum type,
like the one we have already
discover.
But there are a few differences,
with respect to the typical constructor of
traditional sum types.
The first one is that
you can define new exceptions at any time.
This is not the case for traditional sum types.
So this sum type exception is somehow special,
it can be extended dynamically, when you need
it.
On the other side there is also limitations
that comes with this extra power:
the fact
that exceptions cannot be polymorphic.
You must fix the type at the beginning.
Well, to declare an exception, it's extremely
simple
in the system.
You just use the keyword exception,
like here:
in the toplevel we have written
exception E,
and when it returns, the system
will answer just saying:
ok, there is a new
exception declared with the constructor E.
And these are really just constructors.
After the definition, we can just use, you
see as
here,
we just can type E in this case,
and the system says: yes,
that's a value E
of type exception.
Of the exception type.
Well, once you have defined exception,
the first thing you can do we this exception
is
to raise it.
I mean you can tell the system:
I have found an exception, exception E,
please
stop everything and tell the world.
To signal
this exception, we use the raise keyword,
like here: raise E.
The system answers now
exception: E,
saying I have stopped the
computation because I got an exception and
this exception is E.
Let me make it more clear:
when an exception is raised, everything is
immediately stopped, any computation,
and we only get the exceptional value as a
return.
For example here, we have make a definition
where we say first raise E in the expression
that should return the list [1; 2],
and if
we hit return, the system doesn't compute
the list [1; 2], doesn't return 1 and 2,
but just stops with the special exception
E as soon as it sees it.
Let's see this applied
in a more realistic example.
So let's say we want to define a head function
that takes a list,
and gets the first element
which is present in the list.
A natural definition
could look like this:
the function head, that
takes a list.
We define it by pattern matching
the list: is it list of elements ?
Then we return the first element.
But what can we do if the list is empty ?
There is nothing to return.
Well, this is a typical case where
an exception comes in handy.
So let's define an
exception Empty_List.
OK, so choose a meaningful name.
And if we are passed an empty list,
we just raise an exception saying this is
an exceptional condition.
Well, let's see.
So we pass the definition to the toplevel.
We have defined our Empty_List exception.
We define the function head.
OK, so now you see that this function is accepted
by the compiler
that says:
you have the head function taking 'a list and returning 'a.
But actually
in one particular case, it will raise an exception.
Let's test it a bit.
So, we can say, for example, head of the list
[1; 2; 3].
Of course we get 1, which is fine.
And if we call the head function with an empty
list, well as you might expect, we got an
exception now.
This is an exception saying:
well, we couldn't find a meaningful result
to return,
then we got an exceptional situation,
what we get back is an exception.
Well, it's very interesting to raise exceptions,
but it is also fundamental to be able to capture
them and do something with them, in case you
want to handle exceptional situations.
This is done in the OCaml programming language
with the try/with construction.
Here we have an example of the syntax,
so basically you write try, then any expression
you want then
with, and then you have a pattern matching.
What happens ?
Well basically, expression e is evaluated.
If it doesn't raise any exception: fantastic,
the result of the try/with construct is just
the result of e.
But if an exception, let's say E,
is raised,
then this exception is
matched with all the patterns that come after
the with clause.
And here, it is just general
pattern matching, you can use any legal pattern.
If this exception matches some pattern, let's
say pattern i,
then the result of the whole
construct will be the result of evaluating
expression e_i.
Be careful: all of the e_i
must have the same type and must have the
same type as e,
because these are all the
values we return in the exceptional situations
in place of the result of e, of course.
Now, so let's consider an interesting question.
Let's take a list, possibly long list of integers.
We want to multiply all the elements in this
list, and doing it efficiently.
So we have already seen solutions to this
problem,
but now we are considering a corner case which
is interesting:
what happens when inside a
list we find the number 0?
As soon as we find the number 0,
we know that there is no point
in continuing the evaluation of the rest of
the list, the end result will be 0.
So, a straightforward way of implementing this remark is
a definition
like this one.
You see we're defining our
recursive function multl for multiplication
of a list that returns 1 on the empty list,
and when the list is not empty, it checks
whether the result is 0,
at the beginning,
that case just stops the computation and return 0.
And, otherwise, it calls itself recursively on the rest and does the multiplication by a.
OK, this is a definition that works perfectly
well.
We can try it on an example.
For example, on this one.
OK, of course the
result is 0:
see, we can find the 0 in
the middle.
But the point is that this is
not as efficient as it seems,
because indeed
as soon as a 0 is found, in the list,
for
example in this position here, what happens
is that when the expected result is 0
but then all the pending recursive calls have
to be executed,
and this will end up making a
lot of multiplications of the 0 that we get
here as the result, for the element which are
appending there.
So it can take a lot of time,
imagine you have one million integers so you
just find a 0 at the end,
we will need to
make one million multiplications by 0 by coming
back.
So is it possible to be faster than
that?
Yes.
And this is a typical situation
where having exceptions can save you a lot
of computation time.
So let's redo the previous
example but now using an exception to stop
the computation really without coming back
to recursive calls,
instead of just returning 0.
How can this be?
So we define an exception Zero,
that's a meaningful name.
And then, we define our multiplication of
list with
exception, this function here, in a different
way.
What we want to do is to do a computation
like the previous one that will raise a Zero
exception as soon as a 0 integer is found,
then catch the Zero exception and return
as an integer result.
So definition of this
internal function, auxiliary function, is
similar to the previous one,
the only point
is that as soon as we find a 0,
we raise an
exception, we raise exception Zero here.
This will have a net effect of throwing away
all
the recursive callstack,
and just raise a final exception Zero to
the call.
So we can pass this to the interpreter and
see what is going on.
So we can test that it is accepted again.
And again, we can test
it on a similar example.
Here we also get 0, but believe me,
this time it was much faster because
we are throwing away the callstack.
We have seen how to create new exception,
how to raise them, how to handle them.
But it is very interesting to know that in
the
OCaml system,
many runtime errors are also
catched as exceptions and returned to you as
exceptions that you can manipulate.
Well, you remember, in OCaml the type errors
are catched
at compile time,
but there are many other
errors, which are not type errors, that cannot
be catched at compile time.
So these are runtime errors.
Typically, division by zero, incomplete
pattern matching, out-of-bound access to mutable
data structures, and many others.
What is very nice is that in OCaml, when these
errors occur, your program does not crash.
What happens is that the system wraps this
error into an exception which is raised,
and then this exception is something that
you
can handle.
Let's see this on some examples.
OK, so let's try to see what happens if we
make a division by zero.
For example let's divide three by zero.
Well, of course we get an error and system
says that an exception
was raised which is actually named Division_by_zero.
This is really the constructor of the exception
type which is named Division_by_zero.
Other examples: let's try to make an out-of-bounds
access to mutable data structure, for example
an array.
Here we define an array with three elements.
We see here: the first element is
1, second is 2 and third is 3.
But now you
remember arrays in OCaml start from 0 as it
happens in other languages, so if I access
the first element, it's actually v.(0).
But imagine at some time in your program you forget that you are
starting from 0,
and you try to access the
third element by using v.(3) instead of
v.(2).
In that case, well we get another
exception which is an out-of-bounds error
from the array.
But in this case you see,
instead of crashing the program as it can
happen in other languages,
you get just the
runtime error wrapped into an exception that
you can capture, that you can manipulate.
And this is an Invalid_argument "index out of bounds",
actually tells you that at runtime,
there is a right bound check which is performed
for
you by the system.
A third case we want to show is what happens
if you decide to ignore
the recommendation of the compiler,
like for example in this definition of the
function
here,
it is clear, at this point in the course,
that the pattern matching is not complete
because we are not handling the case of the
empty list.
This is just a drop function that
takes a list, drops the first element and
keeps the rest, but what happens if you have
an empty list?
There is nothing to drop.
And we didn't say what is going to happen.
So the compiler, if we send this function
definition to it,
finds that the pattern matching
is not complete and actually the example of
a value which is not matched is exactly the
empty list.
Anyway we can bypass or ignore
this warning and the function is still defined
here.
We can try to use it as it is, of course
as long as we use it on a non-empty list,
everything works.
But when we are trying it on the single case
on which the function
definition was not perfectly done,
we get an error which is a Match_failure
exception.
So at runtime there is a case which was not handled by the pattern matching definition.
But again, the program doesn't crash,
it only raises an exception
that we can catch and handle later on.
To sum up, we have seen how exceptions work.
There are constructors of a special exception
sum type which is extensible.
They can be
declared and raised using very simple to remember
keywords: just exception and raise.
You can handle and capture exceptions using
the try ... with ...
construct.
And they are very useful for signalling
and handling exceptional conditions, for altering
flow control,
for writing more efficient algorithms,
and what is really good to know is that unlike
what it happens in other programming languages,
raising, handling exceptions is extremely
fast.
So please use them if they fit your algorithms.