Welcome back.
So when someone is implementing a module,
does in his mind a well delimited set of features
that are offered by his module.
Now, when he wants to publish this module,
to have the module used by other programmers,
he wants this features to be describe in something
like a user manual
so that they are use in the way they are designed
to.
What does that mean exactly?
Well, functions preconditions must be verified
by the client.
Also the client should not break data invariants
that are the key for data structure to work.
Also the client should not use a definition,
that is internal,
that should be private because it may change
in the future.
So that's like a contract that must be respected
in exchange for the module features.
Moreover the type checker will help us
to enforce the data invariant of the data
structure
and also will prevent a client from using
definitions he shouldn't use.
For the syntax to assign a signature to a
module is the following one:
you use the keyword module, M like in a
standard module definition, :,
and just after the : you write the signature
you want to assign to this module.
In fact you can name a signature so that
you don't have to rewrite it if you have to
write it several time.
To do so you use the keyword module type
followed by the identifier of the signature
and then you just write the definition of
this signature.
Again an identifier of a signature must start
with an uppercase letter.
Then of course you can use this name to constraint
some module implementation.
So let us now define a module for natural
numbers.
A natural number is a positive integer
so we will use the type int to represent a
value of natural number.
We will have only three functions, three values,
the first value is zero that represents
the 0 in natural number
and then we have the ability to go from a
natural number to the successor of this natural
number.
And also from a natural number to its predecessor.
The implementation is straightforward
except that you have to take care not to break
the invariant
that the int that you are using to represent
a natural number is indeed a natural number.
So here you have to take care not to overflow
which means that when you
take the successor of something
that is max_int you don't want to do plus
one otherwise we go to min_int.
You prefer to return 0 in that case
and if n is not max_int it is then between
0 and max_int - 1
so you can do n + 1.
The same kind of reasoning is applied to pred
saying that
you don't want to take the predecessor of
and that time we choose to stay at 0.
So this valid module can be given to the OCaml
toplevel and indeed it is accepted.
And we can try to use it for instance here
I define a function which performs the addition
between two natural numbers x and y,
if you have the fact that x is equal to
0 you return y
because 0 + y is equal to y,
and otherwise you call yourself recursively
by computing (x - 1) + y
and finally you take the successor of this
natural number to get the result of the addition.
So this is working well.
The problem is that it is also easy for a
client to break the abstraction.
Here for instance as I know that t is equal
to int
as a client I can use the module in a bad
way by providing -1 to the function pred
and I get a natural number which is negative
and this is very wrong because it is against
our invariant.
So we have a problem in this example
because some invariant is broken by the programmer
that used a fact that he shouldn't use.
The fact that t is in fact implemented by
integer.
Well we could write a comment in the signature
saying that he should be gentle and don't
use this fact.
But still the temptation can be very hard
to resist.
That's why we will use what is called abstract
types
that will give no choice to the client programmer
but to respect this rule.
So let us come back to our example.
And let's just change just a small thing in
the interface.
So in the signature I will remove the equality
between t and int.
So now in the signature we just know that
there exists some type t
but we know nothing about its implementation.
So let us check that the toplevel accepts
this definition
and indeed inside the inferred signature we
can see that
type t is just declared but no implementation
about type t is given.
So type t is a type identifier that is just
equal to itself
but if I try to apply this pred function
to now an integer I can't,
because for the type checker Naturals.t
is a type that is different from int.
So what we have done with an abstract type
is just to hide the definition of the type.
So now the signature does not publish t's
implementation details anymore.
And the type checker ensures that the clients
cannot use that fact.
So that's exactly why t is called an abstract
type.