So welcome to this final week about functional
programming in OCaml.
So, what do we have so far?
We are able to define toplevel types, functions
and basic values.
So what we have done is to program in the
small,
which means that we have defined very fine
data structures and algorithms,
and what we have seen is that OCaml, the core
language of OCaml,
is great to write these data structures and
algorithms
in a safe, sound and efficient way.
So now, when you have to deal with the development
of a large project,
you have an extra difficulty which is to manage
the complexity of your system.
That can comes from the high number of definitions.
The problem is that sometimes, in a large
system,
you can be lost into the implementation details,
and an answer to that problem is what is called
abstraction in software engineering.
An abstraction is a concept that can be understood
intrinsically,
without a precise knowledge of its implementation.
So its a way to forget about the details,
and understand some part of the system by
itself.
An abstraction can be built on top of other
abstractions,
so that the sytem is built using some vocabulary
that clearly describes the answer to some
problems at some level of abstraction.
In fact when you design a software,
good architecture are made of layers of abstractions.
So, the rules of the game are different now,
and what you want to do is really different
from what you do when you implement algorithms.
The first thing that you want to do is
to be able to split the system into smaller
components,
that can be understood separately,
and also whose development can be delegated
to several programmers.
Then you don't know if two programmers won't
use the same name
so you want to have a way to avoid conflicts.
Also, you want the software engineering to
be respected,
which means that a programmer is not allowed
to break the abstraction,
to go into details that he should not know.
And also, a good property of components is
their ability to be recomposed, reconfigured,
after their development.
In fact, the module system of OCaml fulfills
all these requirements.
And that will be the topic of this final week.
So we will see how to structure software with
modules,
how to hide information.
We will do a small case study about how to
design a library for dictionaries.
We will give some basic notions about what
functors are.
And finally, we will see how nude modules
can be used to compile
and produce a large executable program.
The first thing to know is that a module defines
a namespace.
So we already saw that the dot notation
can be used to access a module component.
When you write List.length,
it is the reference to the length function,
which is defined inside the module List.
Now if you want to avoid writing this List.something,
it is always possible to open the namespace
of the module List,
to implicitly refer to List.length when
you write length.
So just by writing open List, you can be
in that settings.
Now if you open two modules, and they define
identical identifiers,
then the last one will have the priority.
So now, how can you define a module?
The syntax is the following one:
you use the keyword module followed by the
identifier of this module,
and between struct and end,
you just write a sequence of definitions,
that will be part of this module.
The things that you have to know is the fact
that
an identifier of a module must start with
an uppercase letter.
Then, you can just write definitions as you
already know:
value, type, exception definitions, inside
the implementation of the module.
Sometimes you may be interesting of changing
the name of a module for some reason,
so you can also alias a module just by writing:
module, one identifier for the module you
want to define, =, an other module identifier.
So let us see what module implementation looks
like in OCaml.
So we have this module keyword that introduces
a module.
Here we have named this module Stack,
and we used an uppercase letter to start the
identifier.
And between struct we have implemented
several functions and types,
that implement the data structure of Stack.
So we know that Stack is implemented here
by a list,
the empty stack is the empty list,
pushing an element on top of the stack is
adding an element at the beginning of the
list,
and if you want to pop the element that
is on the top of the stack,
then it's not possible if you have an empty
list,
but if you have a non empty list,
you can just return the head of the list,
and the new stack is the tail of the list.
So if we evaluate this, we can see that OCaml
accepts this definition,
and infers what is called a signature,
which is in fact the type of the module,
and it describes the declaration for types,
for example, but also what are the values
provided by the module.
Here we can see that there is a value empty
of type 'a list.
We can use the module, using the dot notation,
here to extract the empty list.
Here to push an element on top of the list,
and here for instance to pop an element of
the list.
If we try to pop again we have an empty
result.
Modules have types too, and these types are
called signature, or interface.
We have seen in the previous example that
OCaml infers signatures of modules.
But in fact the programmer can force a module
to have a specific signature,
and in fact he should do it,
because publishing a well-designed signature
is a very important communication aspect in
a large project,
and that will be the topic of the next sequence.
So we have a syntax to define signatures:
you use the keyword sig, and between sig
and end,
you have declarations for the different components
of your module.
For instance if you have a value,
you use the keyword val, followed by the
identifier of the value,
:, the type of this value.
The other declarations for types and exceptions
are exactly written in
the same way as you can do in a module implementation.
A module can in fact contain other modules,
so that we can create a hierarchy of modules.
And similarly, a signature can also contain
other module signatures.
Now, if you want to refer to a submodule,
you just have to use a path,
so you have to extend the dot notation by
just adding more module name to enter into
the module namespace more deeply.
It is forbidden to define two submodules with
the same name in a module,
but you can define for instance two values
with the same name in a module.
So, if you have defined a module Forest,
you can have a module Tree inside,
to represent a tree of the forest,
and the type definition for trees you can
use
here the type forest, which is defined before
in the module Forest.
When we enter this to the OCaml toplevel,
we can observe that the signature of the module
Forest contains an other signature for the
inner module Tree.
If you want to access to this namespace,
you can just write open
and after that you can construct a Leaf
of a tree.