Welcome back.
So, we have seen in our case study that the
client has a reference to the module Dict.
And we noticed that a more configurable client,
hence a more reusable one,
would let us choose the dictionary implementation
in a second time, externally, when the module
is already compiled.
That will be exactly the purpose of a module
functor.
Our functorized client will have a reference
to a module
which implements the dictionary interface.
So, let us come back to the example of the
case study.
We have this module type for dictionary,
that is unchanged.
And now, we want to be able to reuse a client
afterwards,
on different implementations of this dictionary.
So we introduce a functor which means that
in the code,
we add an argument, but this argument takes
not a value
but a module, Dict here, and we provide
the signature for this module.
The rest of the code is unchanged.
But now, we have not a module but a functor,
that is a parameterized module.
If we have two different implementations for
the dictionary,
like this, on lists, or like that, on binary
search trees,
now I can define not only one client,
but two clients, the first client that is
implemented using the dictionary represented
by lists,
and another client whose dictionaries are
implemented using binary search trees.
A functor is a function from modules to modules.
So, a functor is a module waiting for another
module.
The syntax to define a functor mimics the
definition of a function.
You start with standard syntax for module
definition
and you just add after the identifier,
as an argument, the module that you are expecting.
This module must be constrainted by some signature.
In that case, OCaml is unable to infer the
type of the module of a functor argument.
As any function, a functor can be applied.
So to apply a functor to a module you just
use the name of your functor
and between parentheses the module that you
want to provide to the functor.
In fact, this module can be a module identifier,
but also directly an implementation using
struct and end,
or even an other functor application,
so that you can chain the application of functors
if you want.
The language of signatures is extended to
be able to handle functors.
We have just a new keyword functor with
the type of the argument and the name of the
argument,
an arrow, and a signature.
The type that is in the argument can be mentioned
inside the definition of the signature.
If you goes through the documentation of the
standard library of OCaml,
you will discover two very interesting modules
and very useful ones:
Set and Map.
In fact, these two modules define functors
that are waiting for an other module satisfying
the following signature.
This signature is named OrderedType because
it contains a type t
which is equipped with a function that compares
two values of type t
and produces 0 if these two values are equal,
and -1 if the first one is greater than
the second one,
and 1 otherwise.
Then if you are able to construct such a module,
and you apply the functor Set.Make on it,
then you will get a very large number of functions
that manipulate sets whose elements have type
E.t.
Similarly, if you apply Map.Make on this
module,
you will get a large set of functions manipulating
maps whose keys are of type E.t.
So remember another remark that we have done
about the case study in the last sequence.
We've said that it was a pity that the exception
NotFound cannot be adjusted in a way
that it carries the key that has not been
found.
It would a more informative exception.
But it was not possible because the type parameter
'key should then be shared between the type
of dictionaries
and the type of the exception,
but the type of exceptions in OCaml cannot
be polymorphic.
In fact, such a type parameterization can
be done using a functor.
So, let us come back to our example of the
case study.
We had a signature that was a bit different
from the one that we have here.
So previously we had a parameterized type
with two parameters,
but we said that we want to share the type
parameter 'key
between several definitions.
So we have split this type in two.
And now it is a component of the signature
of the module.
It's simply a type key that should be given
inside the type of the module.
So now, this type key can be used not only
in the definition of functions,
like this, but also in the definition of exception.
So now, NotFound can carry the key.
How can we now implement a module that fulfills
this signature?
Well, we have to provide a way to give this
type key
so we will give it through a module argument.
So Dict is now a functor, it is a function
from module to module.
So it takes a module Key whose signature
is a type t
which is a type for keys,
and also a comparison function working on
keys.
We can use this module inside the implementation
of the functor body,
so type key can be equal to the module Key
which was given as an argument,
dot t, so the type t in the provided module.
That's nice.
After that, the code is essentially the same
as before,
except that during the lookup you can use
now
the comparison function that is found in the
module argument
to compare the keys when you are looking for
some key.
OK, so let's see if this is working.
So, first, evaluate the signature,
after that, the functor,
and we can notice that the inferred signature
indeed introduces a functor with a description
of the signature of its input module.
So now we can apply this functor on a module
that defines the type for key which is equal
to string
and let's say to compare two keys we will
first lowercase them,
so that if there is some cases that are different
between two keys
that means the same,
they will be made equal by this comparison
function.
So this one is accepted.
We now have a dictionary,
and let's try to use it in a client.
So our client is now a functor
that is waiting for a module implementing
the signature for dictionary.
So let's try to evaluate this.
Oww... We have a typing error.
It says "luke" is a string, but you must
provide a Dict.key.
Oh yes, Dict.key is an abstract type,
so there is no reason that it is equal to
string.
So what we have to do is to express the fact
that
here the type key must be equal to string.
OK?
Because after that with this extra information
the program
that was rejected will be accepted.
So what I've written here is what is called
a typing constraint,
that is put on a signature.
It's a way to give more information to the
body of the functor.
So let's see if this is accepted...
Oh yes, it is!
Nice.
Can I continue?
Yes, I can try to now instanciate some archive
using this functor,
and implementing the dictionary using the
first implementation of the dictionary.
Is it accepted?
Oh no... Why?
Yes, I see why.
Dict1 is a module that also has the type
for key that is abstract
so I have to, again, express more information
about the relation
between the type of the key of the output
module
and the type of the key of the input module.
And again, I can use a typing constraint to
do so.
So I will write a new functor for Dict that
says
that the output module will fulfills the typing
constraint
that the type key that is inside this module
is equal to the type key that is provided
in the input module argument.
And now, even if these two types are abstract,
there are made equal in the output of the
functor.
I I try now to apply the ForceArchive functor
to Dict1,
sorry, Dict1 has to be redefined too...
OK, so if I now apply my functor it's accepted,
and moreover I can see that now my exception
is informative,
saying that "r2d2" is not a Jedi.
What we have seen with this example is
first, a very nice way to implement type parameterization
between several components, an exception definition
and values and so on,
but also we have seen that sometimes,
type abstraction must be relaxed a little
bit a posteriori, afterwards.
And this is exactly the role of a type constraint.
It expresses the fact that some typing signature
which is abstract
verifies, satisfies, some constraints, some
equalities with other types.
So when you have a type constraint on a signature
it restricts the usage and the definition
of the functor you are defining.
But in exchange, the functor client will get
more guarantees about abstract types.
The fact that two types for instance share
the same definition even if
you don't know exactly what this definition
is.
The syntax to put a type constraint on a signature
is
just a signature and then a sequence of type
equalities
that are introduced using the keyword with
and separated
using the keyword and.