Welcome back.
So for the moment,
you probably have programmed in OCaml
using the website that we have provided for
this MOOC.
But at some point, you may be interested in
developing real size programs using real world
tools.
So we will see how to compile OCaml programs.
The first thing to know is that extension
of the filename
of an OCaml source code is .ml.
The OCaml language enjoys the separate compilation
property
which means that we can produce an executable
program
in the following way:
you first compile each file separately,
following the dependencies,
and when you have all the compiled units
you can put them together,
link them together,
in order to produce an executable program.
To do so you will use ocamlc
which is a compiler from OCaml to the OCaml
virtual machine,
or ocamlopt which is the compiler from OCaml
code
to native code, which means the code that
your processor is understanding directly.
In the sequel, we will use ocamlc but you
can use the same commands
and they will work with ocamlopt too.
So imagine that you have a project with two
files
a.ml and b.ml,
and that b.ml uses a.ml.
So first, you have to compile a.ml.
The command is ocamlc -c a.ml.
This command will produce two files:
the first one is a .cmo file and it's actually
the compiled code.
In this case, in the case of ocamlc it's
just bytecode that can be interpreted
by the virtual machine.
If you had chosen ocamlopt then you will
produce
a .cmx file,
which will contain machine code.
There is another file that is produced both
by
ocamlc and ocamlopt and that's a .cmi
file.
It's a compiled interface and I will come
back on that
in the next slide.
Now you can compile b.ml using the same
method,
and finally to link a.cmo and b.cmo into
the same executable program,
you use ocamlc -o prog to say that the output
executable program will be names prog,
and after that the list of the compiled units
but in the order of dependencies.
So as a.cmo is used by b.cmo it must come
before b.cmo.
In fact, compilation units are seen as modules
from the programming point of view.
If you have a file named a.ml, then it will
appear as a module A in the program.
The only change in the name is the fact that
the first letter is now in uppercase, so the
filename is capitalized.
If you want to refer in b.ml to a value
x defined in a.ml,
you just write A.x and it will work.
So, as compilation units are modules,
then we should be able to represent also the
interface
of a module.
And that's possible if you write a file named
a.mli,
so 'i' like "interface",
you can define the signature of the module
A that you are defining.
So the content of a.mli is basically what
you would have written
between sig and end when you define a
signature.
So you will write declarations only in that
kind of file.
When a.ml is compiled, the compiler looks
for an interface,
if the programmer wrote an interface it will
use it to compile the interface,
if there is no such file it will use the inferred
module interface,
the one that shows everything.
If you want to compile interfaces separately,
you can do it,
you just have to provide an a.mli file to
the compiler,
it will detect that it is an interface
and produce a .cmi file.
This operation can be interesting if you want
to parallelize
a lot of compilation because when the compilation
of the interface of A is done,
you can compile both the implementation of
A but also in parallel,
the implementation of B,
since this compilation is using only the compiled
interface.
You may wonder, especially if you have programmed
in the C language or Java,
what is the entry point of an OCaml program.
The answer is simple:
there is no such thing.
There is no entry point.
There is no main function in an OCaml program.
The evaluation of a program is the evaluation
of the modules
that compose this program.
And they are evaluated in the order given
at the link time,
so the order that you gave to ocamlc when
you produced the executable program.
And that's all.
As in any programming language
you can aggregate compilation units into a
single file called a library.
To do so, you use a -a command of ocamlc
followed by the list of files that you want
to put inside your library,
and afterwards you just -o option to define
the name of the library you want to use.
The file extension for libraries in OCaml
is .cma.
If you defined a native code library,
its a .cmxa.
Now once you have a library,
it can be used by another program,
exactly as if it were a compilation unit.
To install a library in the system you just
have to copy the compiled files .cmi, .cmo
and .cma
into some directory that you choose to install
your library.
After that, if you want to able to use the
library
to compile another program,
you just use the option -I followed by the
name of the directory
in which the library is installed,
and you will get all the exported values and
modules
that are available in the library.
When you produce the executable program,
you also need to provide the library as an
input
to push it inside the executable program.
To do so, you use again the -I some dir
to configure the compiler to explain
where he can find the library files,
and you have to provide the library file too.
This can be a bit exhausting to do all that
command line,
all that configuration for all the libraries
you use in a program.
Fortunately there exists a tool called findlib
that will automates some generation of the
compilation options
that you want to provide to ocamlc.
Also findlib will take care of finding a
place where to install a library and indexing
the libraries that are installed in your system.
OCaml comes with a build system tool named
ocamlbuild.
Its role is to build compiled files, libraries,
executable programs,
anything that can be produced by the compiler
of OCaml
can also be produced by ocamlbuild.
What is interesting is the fact that ocamlfind
computes for you
the dependencies between the modules.
It is also configurable using a file that
will describe for instance
the libraries that you want to use to compile
your program.
To do so it of course interacts with findlib.
And if there are some aspects that you want
to do that are
very specific to your project,
it is also customizable using plugins that
are written in OCaml.
But most of the time,
when you have a simple program like for instance
just a bunch of ml files that you want to
compile
and modules for instance a.ml that corresponds
to what should do your program,
then just by typing ocamlbuild a.byte,
it will compile a.ml with all its dependencies
and produce an executable program.
At another level,
OCaml has a package manager
and it is called opam.
I won't describe its use
but you can online and you will find enough
documentation
to install it and to use it.
A package is a bunch of libraries and program
files
that are useful to other developments.
So it's a way to build on top of the work
of other people
your projects.
So it's a way to be very productive.
And opam gives you a nice, very nice tool
to be able to get
all the packages that have been developed
by our community.
Of course, maybe some day you will be able
to define your own package,
your own project written in OCaml,
and contribute to our community of programmers.
So thank you a lot
to have followed this course,
and now we hope you are ready to tackle your
first challenge: the project.