Welcome back.
In this case study, we will go into more details
about
how abstract data types can be used to improve
the modularity of programs.
So in this case study, we will define a module
type, an interface,
that corresponds to what expecting from a
module
that provide a data structure for dictionary,
with the functions that work on dictionaries.
So, it's a little story, let's imagine first
that
the designer of the interface wrote something
like that:
the type for dictionary is an association
list,
so a list of pairs, with a key and a value,
and then, there exists an empty dictionary,
a function that takes a dictionary, a key
and a value and
returns a new dictionary that contains all
the keys of the previous dictionary
plus the new key related to the provided value.
There also exists an exception that is raised
when a lookup fails.
And so there is this lookup function
that takes a dictionary, a key,
and returns a value associated to this key
in the dictionary
if it exists, or raise NotFound otherwise.
So, this is a module type, and it is accepted
by the OCaml compiler.
Now, this is an obvious implementation that
I won't detail,
for the signature,
and we can write a client that makes use of
all this definition
to define a module that store some relation
between name and integer,
and it works.
So everything looks fine,
except that the interface is not well designed.
Indeed, imagine the following scenario:
the developer of this module notices that
finally, this implementation based on association
list
is not valid, because it's not really efficient.
The lookup function is linear on the size
of the list.
So he want to change the data structure that
implements the dictionary.
But unfortunately, the interface mentions
the way the dictionary is implemented.
So the client has used this information to
implement this value in this module,
so here force is a list, so its valid to
apply List.map function.
So something is wrong here.
The evolution of the first module, the implementation
of the dictionary,
cannot be done without changing the client.
So imagine that there is an hundred clients
for this module,
they will have to change an hundred clients,
just because you have a badly designed interface.
So imagine now that we have made this type
abstract,
then at the first place it would be impossible
for the client
to write a call like that.
Let us check that the compiler rejects this
code.
Yes, for the reasons that are now clear to
us,
Dict.t is an abstract type,
so even if it internally implemented as an
list,
it's not a list from the outside.
So we have to remove this definition,
and now, we can continue the story and
change the implementation of the dictionary,
to be for instance a binary search tree.
Again, I won't detail this implementation,
except that it's a valid implementation for
dictionary.
Just have to know that,
and indeed the compiler checked that the module
satisfies the dictionary signature.
The nice thing is the fact that
you can reuse exactly the same code for the
client,
and it is a valid code.
Just a final remark:
notice that when I evaluate this module,
the exception Dict.NotFound is raised.
So one of the lookup here failed.
But the exception is not really informative
because I would have loved to have here
the name of the key that was not found
in the dictionary.
So, all this module programming is very nice,
but still, some points can be improved.
The first one is the fact that the exception
that is raised
when a lookup has failed is not very informative.
We would love to write an exception declaration
mentioning not only the fact that the key
is not found,
but which key has been not found.
Yet, that's not directly possible in OCaml,
because exceptions cannot be polymorphic.
Also, our dictionary implementations based
on trees and lists
are using the default polymorphic comparisons
of values
that OCaml provides,
but sometimes it can be convenient to define
another comparison
and that's not really possible in our implementation.
Finally, in the client, the reference to the
module Dict is hardcoded into the code.
So that you can't change it afterwards.
Delaying this choice would make the client
more reusable
because the same code could be used with different
configurations,
depending on the implementation of Dict
that we want to use.
In the next sequence, we will discover functors.
And they will solve all these issues.